<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE Claset PUBLIC "-//EUROSTAT EG6 WG3//CLASET//EN" "http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/ramon/claset/clasetxml.dtd">
<Claset reference="NACE_1_1">
	<Classification id="NACE_1_1" type="Classification">
		<Label qualifier="Usual">
			<LabelText language="EN">Statistical Classification of Economic Activities in the European Community, Rev. 1.1 (2002)</LabelText>
		</Label>
		<Property name="Comment" dataType="AN">
			<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
				<PropertyText type="Content">Statistical Classification of Economic Activities in the European Community, Rev. 1.1 (2002)</PropertyText>
			</PropertyQualifier>
		</Property>
		
		<Level id="5" nbItems="514">
		
		<Level id="1" nbItems="17">
		
		<Level id="2" nbItems="31">
		
		<Level id="3" nbItems="62">
		
		<Level id="4" nbItems="224">
		
		</Level>
		
		</Level>
		
		</Level>
		
		</Level>
		
		</Level>
		<Item id="01" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Agriculture, hunting and related service activities</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">Division 01 first of all distinguishes two basic activities
     •  Production of crop products (01.1: Growing of crops...) and 
     •  Production of animal products (01.2: Farming of animals).

Within 01.1 a distinction is made between
     •  field crops which generally follow a yearly cycle (01.11 and 01.12), such as cereal, vegetable or flower growing 
     •  crops with a long cycle such as plantations (e.g. coffee, cocoa, etc.), vineyards and orchards (01.13). 

Within group 01.2 (Farming of animals), the activities are grouped according to the type of animal and not according to the type of product produced (e.g. meat, milk, hide, etc.) and without distinguishing between total confinement (non-grazing) and open range pasture farming.

Group 01.3 (Mixed farming) breaks with the usual principles for identifying main activity. It accepts that many agricultural holdings have reasonably balanced crop and animal production, and that it would be arbitrary to classify them in one category or the other.

Certain operations such as soil preparation, planting, harvesting, and management, which are normally part of farm operation may be carried out by agricultural support units on a fee or contract basis, as agricultural (01.41) or animal husbandry (01.42) service activities.

Agricultural activity excludes any subsequent processing of the agricultural products (classified under division 15: Manufacture of food products, and division 16: Manufacture of tobacco products), beyond that needed to prepare them for the primary markets.  However, as an exception to the general rule for classification of integrated activities, a unit processing its own agricultural production on the farm is classified to 01, even though the output normally is the product of division 15 and 16. Examples are 
     •  Growing of grapes and production of wine from these 
     •  Growing of olives and production of olive oil from these.

The division excludes field construction (e.g. agricultural land terracing, drainage, preparing rice paddies, etc.) classified in division 45 (Construction) and buyers and cooperative associations engaged in the marketing of farm products classified in section G (Wholesale and retail trade; ...)</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="02" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Forestry, logging and related service activities</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">Forestry covers the production of standing timber as well as the extraction and gathering of wild growing forest materials. Besides the production of timber, forestry results in products which undergo little processing, such as wood for fuel or industrial use (e.g. pit-props, pulpwood, etc.).

Further processing of wood beginning with sawmilling and planing of wood, which is generally done away from the logging area, is classified to Manufacture of wood and wood products (division 20), and production of charcoal is classified under division 24.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="05" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Fishing,  fish farming and related service activities</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="10" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Mining of coal and lignite; extraction of peat</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">The extraction of solid mineral fuels covers underground or open-cast mining and includes operations (e.g. grading, cleaning, etc.) leading to a marketable product including briquetting (e.g. briquettes and ovoids). It does not include coking (23.10).</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="11" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Extraction of crude petroleum and natural gas; service activities incidental to oil and gas extraction, excluding surveying</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes the activities of operating and/or developing oil and gas field properties. Such activities may include completing, and equipping wells; operating separators, emulsion breakers, desilting equipment, and field gathering lines for crude petroleum; and all other activities in the preparation of oil and gas up to the point of shipment from the producing property. The division includes the production of crude petroleum, the mining and extraction of oil from oil shale and oil sands, and the production of natural gas and recovery of hydrocarbon liquids. Support services, on a fee or contract basis, required for the drilling or operation of oil and gas wells are classified in 11.20.

This division excludes
–   refining of petroleum products, see 23.20.
–   test drilling and boring see 45.12
–   geophysical surveying and mapping see 74.20.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="12" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Mining of uranium and thorium ores</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="13" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Mining of metal ores</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes:
–   underground and open-cast extraction of metal ores and native metals
–   preparation of ores:
     •      crushing and grinding of ores, washing of ores
     •      concentrating of ores by magnetic or gravimetric separation
     •      flotation, screening, grading, drying, calcination and roasting of ores.

This division excludes:
–   mining of uranium and thorium ores, see 12.00
–   roasting of iron pyrites, see 24.13
–   production of aluminium oxide, see 27.42.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="14" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Other mining and quarrying</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division covers not only extraction from a quarry, but also dredging of alluvial deposits, rock crushing and the use of salt marshes. The products are used most notably in construction (e.g. sands, stones, etc.), manufacture of materials (e.g. clay, gypsum, calcium, etc.), manufacture of chemicals, etc.

Salt production includes refining salt, which is suitable for human consumption.

This division does not include processing (except crushing, grinding, cleaning, drying, sorting and mixing) of the minerals extracted.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="15" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of food products and beverages</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="16" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of tobacco products</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="17" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of textiles</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes preparation and spinning of textile fibres as well as textile weaving, finishing of textiles and wearing apparel, manufacture of made-up textile articles, except apparel (e.g. household linen, blankets, rugs, cordage, etc.) and manufacture of knitted and crocheted fabrics and articles thereof (e.g. socks and pullovers).

Growing of natural fibres falls under division 01 (Agriculture), while manufacture of synthetic fibres is a chemical process which has to be classified in class 24.70 (Manufacture of man-made fibres). Manufacture of wearing apparel falls under division 18.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="18" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of wearing apparel; dressing and dyeing of fur</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">The clothing industry covers all tailoring (ready-to-wear or made-to-measure), in all materials (e.g. leather, fabric, knitted and crocheted fabrics, etc.), of all items of clothing (e.g. outerwear, underwear for men, women or children; work, city or casual clothing, etc.) and accessories.  There is no distinction made between clothing for adults or children, or between modern and traditional clothing.

Division 18 also includes the fur industry (furskins and wearing apparel).

It does not include the manufacture of knitted and crocheted articles (17.7) and the finishing of wearing apparel (17.30).</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="19" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Tanning and dressing of leather; manufacture of luggage, handbags, saddlery, harness and footwear</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="20" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of wood and of products of wood and cork, except furniture; manufacture of articles of straw and plaiting materials</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes manufacture of wooden products, such as lumber, plywood, veneers, wooden containers, wooden flooring, wooden trusses and prefabricated wooden buildings. The production processes include sawing, planing, shaping, laminating and assembling of wooden products starting from logs that are cut into bolts, or lumber that then may be further cut, or shaped by lathes or other shaping tools. The lumber or other transformed wooden shapes may also be subsequently planed or smoothed, and assembled into finished products, such as wooden containers.

With the exception of sawmills and wood preservation units, the units are grouped into industries mainly based on the specific products manufactured.

It does not include either the manufacture of furniture (36.1), or the installation of not self-manufactured wooden fittings and the like (45.42).</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="21" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of pulp, paper and paper products</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division covers manufacture of pulp, paper or converted paper products. The manufacturing of these products is grouped together because they constitute a series of vertically connected processes. More than one is often carried out in a single unit. There are essentially three activities. The manufacturing of pulp involves separating the cellulose fibres from other impurities in wood or used paper. The manufacturing of paper involves matting these fibres into a sheet. Converted paper products are made from paper and other materials by various cutting and shaping techniques and includes coating and laminating activities. The paper articles may be printed (e.g. wallpaper, gift wrap, etc.), as long as the printed information is not the main purpose.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="22" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Publishing, printing and reproduction of recorded media</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">In general, the units, which are known as publishers, issue copies of works for which they usually possess copyright. Works may be in one or more formats including traditional print form, audio tape, CD-ROM or on-line. Publishers may publish works originally created by others for which they have obtained the rights and/or works that they have created in-house.

The printing activities print products, such as newspapers, books, periodicals, business forms, greeting cards, and other materials, and perform support activities, such as bookbinding, platemaking services, and data imaging. The support activities included here are an integral part of the printing industry, and a product (a printing plate, a bound book or a computer disk or file) that is an integral part of the printing industry is almost always provided by these operations.

Processes used in printing include a variety of methods used to transfer an image from a plate, screen, or computer file to some medium, such as paper, plastics, metal, textile articles, or wood. The most prominent of these methods is to transfer the image from a plate or screen to the medium (lithographic, gravure, screen, and flexographic printing). A rapidly growing new technology uses a computer file to directly &apos;&apos;drive&apos;&apos; the printing mechanism to create the image and new electrostatic and other types of equipment (digital or non-impact printing).

Though printing and publishing are often carried out by the same unit (e.g. a newspaper), it is less and less the case that these distinct activities are carried out in the same unit.

This division includes publishing of newspapers, magazines, other periodicals and books.

This division excludes publishing of software, see 72.21.

On-line publishing, not in connection with other publishing, is in 72.40.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="23" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of coke, refined petroleum products and nuclear fuel</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division is based on the transformation of crude petroleum and coal into usable products and also includes the nuclear industries. It is the manufacturing part of the energy sector which begins in section C (Mining and quarrying) and is also present in section E (Electricity, gas and water supply).  The dominant process is petroleum refining that involves the separation of crude petroleum into component products through such techniques as cracking and distillation.

This division includes only manufacture of gases with lower purity (less than 95% for ethane, ethylene and butane, less than 90% for propane (propylene), butene (butylene) and butadiene).

This division also covers the manufacture for own account of characteristic products (e.g. coke, butane, propane, petrol, kerosene, fuel oil, nuclear fuel, etc.) as well as processing services (e.g. custom refining, treatment of nuclear waste).

Not included is manufacture of such gases with higher purity (24.14), manufacture of industrial gases (24.11), extraction of natural gas (methane, ethane, butane or propane) (11.10), and manufacture of fuel gas, other than petroleum gases (e.g. coal gas, water gas, producer gas, gasworks gas) (40.21).</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="24" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of chemicals and chemical products</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="25" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of rubber and plastic products</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="26" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of other non-metallic mineral products</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="27" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of basic metals</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes the activities of smelting and/or refining ferrous and nonferrous metals from ore, pig or scrap, using electrometallurgical and other process metallurgical techniques.  The output of smelting and refining, usually in ingot form, is used in rolling, drawing, and extruding operations to make sheet, strip, bar, rod, or wire, and in molten form to make castings and other basic metal products.

This subsection also covers the manufacture of metal alloys and superalloys by introducing other chemical elements to pure metals.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="28" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of fabricated metal products, except machinery and equipment</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">While Division 28 deals with the manufacture of &quot;pure&quot; metal products (such as parts, containers and structures), usually with a static, immovable function, Divisions 29-36 concern combinations or assemblies of such metal products (sometimes with other materials) into more complex units which, unless they are purely electrical, electronic or optical, work with moving parts.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="29" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of machinery and equipment n.e.c.</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">Division 29 covers the manufacture of machinery and equipment which independently act on materials either mechanically or thermally or perform operations on materials (such as handling, spraying, weighing or packing), including their mechanical components which produce and apply force, and any specially manufactured primary parts.  This category includes fixed and mobile or hand-held devices, regardless of whether they are for industrial, building and civil engineering, agricultural, military or home use.  

Division 29 distinguishes between the manufacture of general-purpose machinery and components and those with special applications.  The headings begin with &quot;Manufacture of ...&quot;:

–   motors and engines (except electric motors), turbines, pumps, compressors, valves and transmissions 
–   ovens, burners, lifting and handling equipment, cooling and ventilation equipment, other general-purpose machinery (e.g. packaging equipment, weighing machines and water purification equipment)
–   agricultural machinery, machine tools, machinery for other specific industrial purposes (e.g. for metal production, building and civil engineering, mining or the manufacture of foodstuffs, textiles, paper, printed matter, plastic and rubber products)
–   weapons and munitions
–   domestic appliances (electrical and non-electrical).

The manufacture of weapons and special equipment for passenger or freight transport within demarcated premises also belongs to this division.

The manufacture of metal products for general use (Division 28), associated control devices, computer equipment, measurement and testing equipment, electricity distribution and control apparatus (Divisions 30-33) and general-purpose motor vehicles (Divisions 34 and 35) is excluded.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="30" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of office machinery and computers</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">The manufacture of office machinery (e.g. photocopiers, cash registers, etc.) and computer equipment (e.g. computers,  word processors and peripherals), is considered to include installation, but not maintenance (72.5), software design (72.2) or the manufacture of electronic components (32.1).

These machines are often leased (71.3: Renting of other machinery and equipment), but if they are leased by the manufacturer, this is simply a form of sale of production.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="31" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of electrical machinery and apparatus n.e.c.</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="32" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of radio, television and communication equipment and apparatus</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division covers the manufacture of  equipment for broadcasting and transmission, receivers, recorders and reproduction equipment.  The division covers all intermediate products from professional equipment to that for the general public.

It should be pointed out that the installation and repair of professional equipment are also covered by this division.

On the other hand, the repair of household equipment falls under 52.7 (Repair of personal and household goods) and the installation of wiring, aerials or alarms falls under construction (45.3:  Building installation).</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="33" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of medical, precision and optical instruments, watches and clocks</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">Division 33 also includes the installation and repair of such industrial equipment, although the repair of personal goods falls under group 52.7 (Repair of personal and household goods).

Division 33 covers not only scientific and technical instruments (e.g. electro-diagnostic apparatus, avionic equipment, etc.) but also photographic and cinematographic equipment, industrial process control equipment, and personal goods (e.g. watches, spectacles, etc.).</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="34" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of motor vehicles, trailers and semi-trailers</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="35" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of other transport equipment</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="36" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Manufacture of furniture; manufacturing n.e.c.</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">Please note that division 36 is a residual division. The usual criteria for grouping classes into divisions have not been applied here.

Repair of products from division 36 generally fall under group 52.7 (repair of personal and household goods), except repair of furniture, musical instruments, professional sports equipment, automatic bowling alley equipment and the like.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="37" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Recycling</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes:
–   processing of waste and scrap and other articles, whether used or not, into secondary raw material. A transformation process is required, either mechanical or chemical. Typical is that in terms of commodities, input consist of waste and scrap, the input being sorted or unsorted but normally unfit for further direct use in an industrial process whereas the output is made fit for direct use in an industrial manufacturing process. The resulting secondary raw material is to be considered as an intermediate good, with a value but is not a final new product.

This division excludes:
–   manufacture of new final products from (whether or not self-manufactured) secondary raw material, see 14 to 36
–   wholesale of waste and scrap, including collecting, sorting, separating, stripping of used goods such as cars in order to obtain reusable parts, (re-)packing, storage and delivery, but without a real transformation process, see 50, 51, 52
–   wholesale or retail sale of second-hand goods, see 50, 51, 52.50
–   treatment of waste, not for further use in an industrial manufacturing process, but with the aim of disposal, see 90.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="40" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Electricity, gas, steam and hot water supply</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="41" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Collection, purification and distribution of water</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="45" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Construction</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes general construction and special trade construction for buildings and civil engineering, building installation and building completion. It includes new work, repair, additions and alterations, the erection of pre-fabricated buildings or structures on the site and also constructions of a temporary nature.

General construction is the construction of entire dwellings, office buildings, stores and other public and utility buildings, farm buildings, etc., or the construction of heavy constructions such as motorways, roads, streets, bridges, tunnels, railways, airfields, harbours and other water projects, irrigation systems, sewerage systems, industrial facilities, pipelines and electric lines, sports facilities, etc. This work can be carried-out on own account or on a fee or contract basis. Portions of the work or sometimes the whole of the practical work can be carried out by subcontractors.

Special trade construction includes the construction of parts of buildings and civil engineering works or preparation for this purpose. It is usually specialized in one aspect common to different structures, requiring specialized skills or equipment. Activities such as pile-driving, foundation work, water well drilling, carcass work, concrete work, brick laying, stone setting, scaffolding, roof covering, etc., are covered. The erection of steel structures is included provided that the parts are not produced by the same unit. Special trade construction will mostly be carried out under subcontract, but especially in repair construction it is done directly for the owner of the property.
 
Building installation activities includes the installation of all kind of utilities that make the construction function as such. These activities are usually performed at the site of the construction, although parts of the job may be carried-out in a workshop. Included are activities such as plumbing, installation of heating and air-conditioning systems, aerials, alarm systems and other electrical work, sprinkler systems, elevators and escalators, etc. Also included are insulation work (water, heat, sound), sheet metal work, commercial refrigeration work, the installation of illumination and signalling systems for roads, railways, airports, harbours, etc. Repair work relating to the above mentioned activities is also included. 

Building completion activities encompass activities that contribute to the completion or finishing of a construction such as glazing, plastering, painting and decorating, floor and wall tiling or covering with other materials like parquet, carpets, wallpaper, etc., floor sanding, finish carpentry, acoustical work, cleaning of the exterior, etc Repair work relating to the above mentioned activities is also included.

This division excludes:
 –   lawn and garden installation and maintenance and tree surgeons activities, see 01.41 
 –  manufacture of building materials, see section C and D
 –  construction activities directly related to extraction of oil and natural gas,  see 11.20. However, the construction of buildings, roads, etc., on the mining site remains in this class
 –  erecting or installing industrial equipment, see section D (e.g. installation of industrial furnaces, turbines, etc.).
 –  erection of complete prefabricated buildings or structures from self-manufactured parts is classified in the relevant category in manufacturing, depending on the material chiefly used, except if the chief material is concrete, in which case it remains classified here 
 –  installation of self-manufactured carpentry or joinery is classified in the relevant category in manufacturing, depending on the material used, e.g. of wood in 20.30 (Manufacture of builders&apos; carpentry and joinery)
 –  erection of metal structures from self-manufactured parts, see  28.11  
 –  architectural and engineering activities are classified in class 74.20 (Architectural and engineering activities and related technical consultancy).
 –  project management for constructions, see  74.20 
 –  cleaning of windows, inside as well as outside, chimneys, boilers, interiors, etc., see 74.70</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="50" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Sale, maintenance and repair of motor vehicles and motorcycles; retail sale of automotive fuel</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes:
–   all activities (except manufacture and renting) related to motor vehicles and motorcycles, including lorries and trucks:
     •   wholesale and retail sale of new and second-hand vehicles
     •   maintenance and repair
     •   wholesale and retail sale of parts and accessories
     •   activities of commission agents involved in wholesale or retail sale of vehicles
     •   washing, polishing and towing of vehicles, etc.

This division also includes:
–   retail sale of automotive fuel and lubricating or cooling products.

This division excludes:
–   renting of motor vehicles, see 71.10
–   renting of motorcycles, see 71.21.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="51" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Wholesale trade and commission trade, except of motor vehicles and motorcycles</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes:
–   resale (sale without transformation) of new and used goods to retailers, to industrial, commercial, institutional or professional users; or to other wholesalers; or acting as agents in buying merchandise for, or selling merchandise to, such persons or companies:
     •   activities of wholesale merchants, jobbers, industrial distributors, exporters, importers, cooperative buying associations, merchandise and commodity brokers, commission merchants and agents and assemblers, buyers and cooperative associations engaged in the marketing of farm products.

This division also includes:
–   the usual manipulations involved in wholesale such as assembling, sorting and grading of goods in large lots, break bulks, repacking and bottling, redistribution in smaller lots, e.g. pharmaceuticals; storage, refrigeration, delivery and installation of goods on own account
–   packing of solid goods and bottling of liquid or gaseous goods, including blending and filtering on own account.

This division excludes:
–   wholesale of motor vehicles, caravans and motorcycles, see 50.10, 50.40
–   wholesale of motor accessories, see 50.30, 50.40
–   renting and leasing of goods, see 71
–   packing of solid goods and bottling of liquid or gaseous goods, including blending and filtering for third parties, see 74.82.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="52" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Retail trade, except of motor vehicles and motorcycles; repair of personal and household goods</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes:
–   resale (sale without transformation) of new and used goods mainly to the general public for personal or household consumption or utilization, by shops, department stores, stalls, mail-order houses, hawkers and peddlers, consumer cooperatives, etc.
–   Retail trade is classified first by type of sale outlet (retail trade in stores: groups 52.1 to 52.5; retail trade not in stores: group 52.6). Retail trade in stores is further subdivided into retail sale of new goods (groups 52.1 to 52.4) and retail sale of used goods (group 52.5). For retail sale of new goods in stores there exists a further distinction between specialized retail sale (groups 52.2 to 52.4) and non-specialized retail sale (group 52.1). The above groups are further subdivided by the range of products sold. Sale not via stores lists the forms of trade (e.g. mail-order, markets, door-to-door, by vending machines , etc.).

This division also includes:
–   repair and installation of personal or household goods whether or not done in combination with retail sale
–   retail sale by commission agents
–   activities of retail auction houses.

This division excludes:
–   sale of motor vehicles, motorcycles and their parts and of fuel for these articles, see 50
–   trade in cereals, grains, ores, crude petroleum, industrial chemicals, iron and steel and industrial machinery and equipment, see 51
–   sale of food and drinks for consumption on the premises and sale of take-away food, see 55.30, 55.40, 55.51
–   renting and hiring of personal and household goods to the general public, see 71.40.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="55" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Hotels and restaurants</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">The section comprises the provision to customers of lodging and/or prepared meals, snacks, and beverages for immediate consumption. The section includes both accommodation and food services because the two activities are often combined at the same unit.

There is some overlap between activities in section H, as the sale of beverages is an independent activity, yet it is at the same time part of a restaurant activity (providing meals, with drinks) and in the latter case sale of beverages is classified together with sale of meals in 55.3 (Restaurants). Similarly, a restaurant activity is a specific activity, but may also be implicitly included in lodging.
 
Lodging units provide lodging or short-term accommodations for travellers, vacationers and others.

There is a wide range of units. Some provide lodging only; while others provide meals and recreational facilities, as well as lodging. The type of complementary services provided may vary from unit to unit.

Restaurant activities provide complete meals fit for immediate consumption, wheter traditional restaurants, self-service or take-away restaurants as well as permanent or temporary fish and chips stands and the like with or without seating. Decisive is the fact that meals fit for immediate consumption are offered, not the kind of facility providing them.

Excluded is the production of meals not fit for immediate consumption or not planned to be consumed immediately or of prepared food which is not considered to be a meal (see 15: Manufacture of food products and beverages). Also excluded is the sale of not self-manufactured food which is not considered to be a meal or of meals which are not fit for immediate consumption (see section G: Wholesale and retail trade; ...).</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="60" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Land transport; transport via pipelines</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="61" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Water transport</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="62" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Air transport</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes:
–   transport of passengers or freight by air or via space.

This division excludes:
–   crop spraying, see 01.41
–   overhaul of aircraft or aircraft engines, see 35.30
–   aerial advertising, see 74.40
–   aerial photography, see 74.81.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="63" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Supporting and auxiliary transport activities; activities of travel agencies</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="64" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Post and telecommunications</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="65" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Financial intermediation, except insurance and pension funding</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes:
–   the activity of obtaining and redistributing funds other than for the purpose of insurance or pension funding or compulsory social security

Note:
–   National institutional arrangements are likely to play a significant role in determining the classification of units within this division
–   Credit-card activities are classified according to type of operator</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="66" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Insurance and pension funding, except compulsory social security</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="67" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Activities auxiliary to financial intermediation</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes:
–   provision of services involved in or closely related to financial intermediation, but not themselves involving financial intermediation</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="70" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Real estate activities</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="71" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Renting of machinery and equipment without operator and of personal and household goods</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes:
–   operational leasing which is normally long-term renting

This division excludes:
–   financial leasing which is normally a special form of credit granting, see 65.21</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="72" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Computer and related activities</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="73" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Research and development</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes three types of research and development:
–   basic research:
     •   experimental or theoretical work undertaken primarily to acquire new knowledge of the underlying foundations of phenomena and observable facts, without particular application or use in view
–   applied research:
     •   original investigation undertaken in order to acquire new knowledge, directed primarily towards a specific practical aim or objective
–   experimental development:
     •   systematic work, drawing on existing knowledge gained from research and/or practical experience, directed to producing new materials, products and devices, to installing new processes, systems and services, and to improving substantially those already produced or installed</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="74" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Other business activities</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="75" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Public administration and defence; compulsory social security</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="80" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Education</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes:
–   public as well as private education at any level or for any profession, oral or written as well as by radio and television

It includes both education by the different institutions in the regular school system at its different levels as well as adult education, literacy programmes, etc.

For each level of initial education the classes include special education for physically or mentally handicapped pupils.

Adult education which is similar in content to the education given at specific levels is included with that level.

This division also includes:
–   other education such as driving schools.

This division excludes:
–   education primarily concerned with recreation such as bridge or golf, see 92.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="85" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Health and social work</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="90" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Sewage and refuse disposal, sanitation and similar activities</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">This division includes:
–   collection and treatment of household and industrial waste, not for a further use in an industrial manufacturing process, but with the aim of disposal and resulting a product of little or no value.

This division also includes:
–   other activities such as street cleaning and snow removal, etc.

This division excludes:
–   processing of waste and scrap and other articles into secondary raw material. A real transformation process is required. The resulting secondary raw material is fit for direct use in an industrial manufacturing process and is not a final product, see 37.10 and 37.20
–   wholesale (purchase and sale) in waste and scrap, including collecting, sorting, packing, dealing, etc., but without a real transformation process, see 51.57.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="91" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Activities of membership organizations n.e.c.</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="92" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Recreational, cultural and sporting activities</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="93" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Other service activities</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item><Item id="95" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Activities of households as employers of domestic staff</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">NOTE: This division is strictly limited to the activities of households as employers of domestic personnel such as maids, cooks, waiters, valets, butlers, laundresses, gardeners, gatekeepers, stable-lads, chauffeurs, caretakers, governesses, babysitters, tutors, secretaries, etc. It allows the domestic personnel employed to state the activity of their employer in censuses or studies, even though the employer is an individual.

The product, which is self-consumed, is considered non-market and assessed according to the cost of the personnel in the national accounts.  These services cannot be provided by companies.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="96" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Undifferentiated goods producing activities of private households for own use</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">NOTE: This division is strictly limited to the activities of households in production units that operate at the subsistence level producing mixed goods for food, shelter and clothing for own consumption. However, household units primarily engaged in a productive activity (non-market) such as agriculture, are classified to the appropriate NACE agriculture category, rather than classified in 96.</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="97" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Undifferentiated services producing activities of private households for own use</LabelText>
</Label>

					<Property name="ExplanatoryNote">
					<PropertyQualifier name="PlainText" language="EN">
<PropertyText type="Content">NOTE: This division is strictly limited to the activities of household primarily engaged in undifferentiated combinations of subsistence service</PropertyText>
</PropertyQualifier>

					</Property>
					</Item><Item id="99" idLevel="3"> <Label qualifier="Usual">
<LabelText language="EN">Extra-territorial organizations and bodies</LabelText>
</Label>
</Item>
	</Classification>
</Claset>
